José Jair Santanna

Ph.D. Researcher, Lecturer, Network Security Specialist & (Big) Data Analyst

Contact

Drienerlolaan 5, Zilverling 5110, 7522 NB Enschede, The Netherlands.

+31 (6) 42330703

http://jairsantanna.com j.i.santanna@utwente.nl

Languages

portuguese native english fluency spanish comprehension dutch comprehension

Programming

Bash, Python, C#,SQL PIG, Spark & Impala

Professional Objective

A research & development position with focus on network security and the use of big data technologies to improve network data analysis. A position where I can transfer my enthusiasm, knowledge, skills and experience into meaningful innovation that improve the security in computer networks, specially in the Internet.

Education

2013–Now **Doctor** in Computer Science University of Twente, The Netherlands

"The DDoS as a \$ervice Phenomenon".

2010–2012 Master in Computer Science Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil

"A BPM-based Solution for Inter-domain Circuit Management". The outcome of this work generated a product still in use by the Brazilian National Education

and Research Network (RNP) (Link: http://meican.cipo.rnp.br/).

2005–2010 **Bachelor** in Computer Engineer Federal University of Pará, Brazil

"A Comparative Evaluation of DCCP Protocol in a Experimental Mesh Network."

Experience

Technical Adviser

2016 To the Dutch National Cyber Security Center and the Scientific Research & Documen-

on **Center** The Neth

For the production of a report on "Cyber metrics 2016: DDoS and Malware"

requested by the Dutch Ministry of Security and Justice.

2016 To the Yokohama National University Japan

For the production of a report on "Reflection & Amplification DDoS attacks" requested by the *Japanese Ministry of Internal Affairs and Communications*.

Assistant Professor

2012–2013 University of Santa Cruz do Sul (UNISC)

Santa Cruz do Sul, Brazil

Tasks & Responsibilities: Supervise students and teach the following courses: Computer Networks, Computer Network Management, and Digital Systems.

Guest Lecturer

2015 & 2016 Product Design to Online Business (course) University of Twente, The Netherlands

Audience: bachelor students of industrial engineering and business information

technology.

2015 **Network Security (course)** University of Twente, The Netherlands

Audience: master and bachelor students of computer science, electrical engineer, and telematics from the University of Twente, 3TU cyber security, and

members of ICT labs.

2015 Cybercrime & Cybersecurity (minor) University of Twente, The Netherlands

Audience: bachelor students from University of Twente, European Research Center for Information (ERCIS), Westfälische Wilhelms - Univerität Münster, Uni-

versität Innsbruck, and University of Leicester.

Software Developer

2015-Now **Distributed Denial of Service Attacks Database (DDoSDB)**

Link: http://bit.ly/ddos_db

An initiative to develop the largest open database with DDoS attacks.

Languages: Python, Bash, Pig Latin & Apache Impala

2010–2011 Management Environment of Inter-domain Circuits for Advanced Networks (MEICAN)

Link: http://meican.cipo.rnp.br/

Development of an Executable Network Management Policies Editor sponsored

by the Brazilian National Education and Research Network (RNP).

Language: WS-BPEL

2009 Support for Planning Sustainable Electrical Power Generation via Vegetable Oil.

Desktop application sponsored by Eletronorte, subsidiary of the major Brazilian

power utility (Eletrobrás). Language: C#.Net & mySQL

Student Supervisor

[M.Sc. Degree] Joey de Vries [Cum Laude], Justyna Chromik [Cum Laude], Wouter de Vries, Mark Wierbosch, and Jarmo van Lenthe.

[B.Sc. Degree] Roeland Krak, Max Kerkers, Dirk Maan, Jochum Börger, and Guilherme Dressler.

International Conference Reviewer

IFIP Networking (2014–2016), IEEE/IFIP Network Operations and Management Symposium (2014 & 2016), Asia-Pacific Network Operations and Management Symposium (2013 & 2014), IFIP/IEEE Integrated Management (2015), International Conference on Autonomous Infrastructure, Management and Security (2015), International Conference on Network and Service Management (2013–2015), EUNICE Conference (2013) & IEEE Symposium on Computers and Communications (2011).

Awards

2015	Best Ph.D. 'Elevator Pitch' (1	St Place)	CTIT Symposium, University of Twente
2015	Best Poster (3 rd Place)		CTIT Symposium, University of Twente
2015	Best Paper Award	autonomous Infrastructure,	Management and Security Conference
2015	Top Papers Nomination Brazi	ilian Symposium on Comp	uter Networks and Distributed Systems
2010	Student Award (3 rd Place)	Computer En	gineer, Federal University of Pará, Brazil

Communication Skills

More than 30 presentations in the last 3 years (see in: http://www.slideshare.net/jjcsantanna), among those I highlight:

2015	Oral Presentation	at Logius (part of the Dutch Ministry of the Interior and Kingdom Relations).
2015	Oral Presentation t	to the Dutch National Management Organization of Internet Providers (NBIP).
2015	Oral Presentation	to the Dutch National Cyber Security Centrum (NCSC).
2013 & 2015	Oral Presentation	at the 31 th and 36 th IRTF Network Management Research Group (NMRG).

Scientific Appendix

Description of Ph.D. Research

Publications

П

DDoS 3.0 - How Terrorists Bring Down the Internet

Aiko Pras, José Jair Santanna, Jessica Steinberger, Anna Sperotto International GI/ITG Conference, MMB & DFT, 2016

Booter websites characterization: Towards a list of threats

Justyna Joanna Chromik, José Jair Santanna, Anna Sperotto, Aiko Pras Brazilian Symposium on Computer Networks and Distributed Systems (SBRC), 2015

Inside Booters: An Analysis on Operational Databases

José Jair Santanna, Romain Durban, Anna Sperotto, Aiko Pras IFIP/IEEE International Symposium on Integrated Network Management (IM), 2015

Booters - An Analysis of DDoS-as-a-Service Attacks.

José Jair Santanna, Roland Rijswijk-Deij, Anna Sperotto, Rick Hofstede, Mark Wierbosch, Lisandro Zambenedetti Granville, Aiko Pras

IFIP/IEEE International Symposium on Integrated Network Management (IM), 2015

How Asymmetric Is the Internet? A Study to Support the Use of Traceroute

Wouter Vries, José Jair Santanna, Anna Sperotto, Aiko Pras International Conference on Autonomous Infrastructure, Management and Security (AIMS), 2015

Characterisation of the Kelihos.B Botnet

Max Kerkers, José Jair Santanna, Anna Sperotto

International Conference on Autonomous Infrastructure, Management and Security (AIMS), 2014

Towards Validation of the Internet Census 2012

Dirk Maan, José Jair Santanna, Anna Sperotto, Pieter-Tjerk Boer EUNICE/IFIP International Workshop (EUNICE), 2014

Characterizing and Mitigating The DDoS-as-a-Service Phenomenon

José Jair Santanna, Anna Sperotto

International Conference on Autonomous Infrastructure, Management and Security (AIMS), 2014

Through the Internet of Things - A Management by Delegation Smart Object Aware System (MbDSAS)

Marcelo Marotta, Felipe Carbone, José Jair Santanna, Liane Tarouco *IEEE Computer Software and Applications Conference (COMPSAC)*, 2013

A BPM-based solution for inter-domain circuit management

José Jair Santanna, Juliano Wickboldt, Lisandro Zambenedetti Granville IEEE Network Operations and Management Symposium (NOMS), 2012

Internet of Things in healthcare: Interoperatibility and security issues

Liane Tarouco, Leandro Bertholdo, Lisandro Zambenedetti Granville, Lucas Arbiza, Marcelo Marotta, José Jair Santanna

IEEE International Conference on Communications (ICC), 2012